Finding Aid for the Al Gilks Papers LSC.1324
UCLA Library Special Collections
Al Gilks papers
1920s-1970s
1920s-1950s
UCLA Library Special Collections
Gilks, Alfred
LSC.1324
1.0 Linear Feet (2 flat boxes)
Cameraman and cinematographer Al Gilks is credited with over sixty films. The collection consists of photographs, clippings, scripts, and printed trade publications related to Gilks?s career from the 1920s to the 1950s. Additionally there are mounted photographs related to his involvement with William K. Vanderbilt film, Over the Seven Seas.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9969820173606533
Biography/History
Al Gilks was born ca. 1892. He served in the U.S. Navy during World War I. He started his career as a cameraman in 1918. During World War II, Gilks served as a member of the Field Photographic Unit of the Office of Strategic Services under John Ford and was involved in the filming of the ?Canal Report?. Gilks worked at Paramount Studios for many years but was also involved in productions for other studios including MGM, RKO Radio Pictures, and C.V. Whitney Pictures. During his career, Gilks worked with the likes of Dorothy Arzner and Sam Wood, among others. His motion picture credits includes over sixty films such as An American in Paris, North of 36, Old Ironsides, Ruggles of Red Gap and Dr. Kildare features. In 1922, Gilks became a member of the American Society of Cinematographers. While filming Old Ironsides in 1926, Gilks's Navy background was useful for capturing the natural sailing conditions and operation of one of the first "nautical" cameras. In 1932, Gilks was involved in Over the Seven Seas, a production documenting William K. Vanderbilt?s round-the-world cruise for the Marine Museum. In 1951, Gilks shared the Academy Award in cinematography for his work on the MGM production, An American in Paris. Gilks retired in 1960. He died in 1970 from a heart attack in Hollywood, California.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of material related to the career of cinematographer Al Gilks. Included are photographs, clippings, scripts, and printed trade publications. Among the photographs are 67 mounted images representing Gilks?s involvement with the William K. Vanderbilt film, Over the Seven Seas, a small number of publicity photographs from Old Ironsides, and a small number of stills and photographs from unidentified film projects. Scripts include Rius the Widower, Ruggles of Red Gap sequence B pages, and the television series Halls of Ivy. Clippings represent writings about Gilks and/or projects in which he was involved, such as Old Ironsides. A small number of trade publications publicize the 24th Academy Award winners, which included Gilks. Materials in this collection represent only a small portion of Gilks?s career.
Cinematographers -- United States -- Archives.; Photographs.; Gilks, Alfred--Archive.
- Academy Award winners publicity featured in various publications., 1952 Mar-April. (Box 2)
  General note
  American Cinematographer, The Film Daily, Hollywood Reporter, Variety,
- Academy Awards photographs., no date. (Box 1)
- Academy Awards presentation program., 1951. (Box 2)
- Academy Awards telegrams., 1952. (Box 1)
- American Cinematographer., 1940s, 1952, 1969. (Box 2)
  7 selected issues.
- American in Paris (An) - typed manuscript narrative by Gilks (10 pages)., no date. (Box 1)
- American Society of Cinematographers membership plaque., 1922. (Box 2)
- Clippings., 1930, 1952. (Box 1)
- Clippings., 1920s-1930s. (Box 1)
- Correspondence., 1926-1957. (Box 1)
- Daily Review Today article about Al Gilks., 1929 Feb. (Box 2)
- Daily Variety., 1930s, 1950s, 1970s. (Box 2)
  8 selected issues.
- Ephemera., no date. (Box 1)
  COI and Navy identification badges, Italian lire note, Russian ruble note, and three unidentified negatives.
- Gilks' Film credits' list., ca. 1955. (Box 1)
- Halls of Ivy (The) - teleplay by Barbara Merlin., 1954. (Box 1)
  Episode: Faculty Follies (#2).
- Halls of Ivy (The) - television script., no date. (Box 1)
  Episode appears to be: Note the Quote.
- Hollywood Reporter (The)., 1930s, 1950s, 1970s. (Box 2)
  12 selected issues.
- International Photographer., 1931, 1948, 1949, 1952, 1954. (Box 2)
  6 selected issues.
- International Photographer issue featuring Gilks on cover (multiple copies)., 1947. (Box 2)
- Mariona Rebull and El viudo Rius clippings., no date. (Box 1)
  See also Rius the Widower.
- Mariona Rebull and El viudo Rius photographs., no date. (Box 1)
- North of 36 - article by Gilks., 1925 Jan. (Box 2)
- Old Ironsides - clippings., 1926. (Box 1)
- Old Ironsides - publicity., 1926-1927. (Box 2)
- Old Ironsides - stills., no date. (Box 1)
- Over the Seven Seas - contract., 1931 April. (Box 2)
- Over the Seven Seas - mounted photographs (31 items)., no date. (Box 4)
- Over the Seven Seas - mounted photographs (36 items)., no date. (Box 3)
- Photographs and negative from unidentified projects., no date. (Box 1)
- Photographs and stills from unidentified projects., no date. (Box 1)
- Photographs inscribed to Gilks., no date. (Box 1)
- Printed Material., 1934, 1970. (Box 2)
  Construction of Boulder Dam pamphlet, the Topographical Quarterly and the World map.
- Programs., no date. (Box 2)
  Two Weeks with Love and Excuse my Dust.
- Rius the Widower - shooting script., no date. (Box 1)
  See also Mariona Rebull and El viudo Rius.
- Ruggles of Red Gap - Sequence B script material., no date. (Box 2)
- To Have and to Hold - negatives., no date. (Box 1)